Preservers of the Past: Indiana's County Historical Societies 1995-1997 ohrc089
Center for Documentary Research and Practice
Preservers of the Past: Indiana's County Historical Societies
1995-1997
Center for Documentary Research and Practice
Indiana University Center for the Study of History and Memory
ohrc089
11 Interviews Audio files, transcripts, and collateral materials
This project contains interviews of members of Indiana county historical societies. The counties included are La Porte, Monroe, Noble, Jefferson, Wells, Randolph, Tippecanoe, Vigo, and Johnson. The interviewees discuss local history and the development of the historical society in their area. They describe society events, funding, exhibits, and publications. The members also describe their connections to their local history. They explain why they believe local history should be preserved and the role of the historical society.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains eleven interviews conducted over three years. The interviews range from 44 to 110 minutes. All interviews consist of audio tapes and typed transcripts.
Acquisition Information
Oral history interviews conducted by the Indiana University Center for the Study of History and Memory from 1968 to the present, with particular focus on the history of twentieth-century America and the Midwest.
- Bender, Paul; Foster, James, April 11, 1997; 95-026; Truesdell, Barbara; 52 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 81 minutes; index; Wells County Historical Society Quarterly Newsletter
  Access Status
  Open
  Scope and Content Note
  Paul Bender and James Foster share information about their educations and careers. They discuss their involvement with the Wells County Historical Society and the community it serves. They discuss the growth and changes of the society. This includes the museum's transformations and growth and decline in membership. Foster and Bender continue with discussion of funding for the Historical Society.
  educator; electrical engineer; hospital administrator; Berne, Indiana; Bluffton, Indiana; Geneva, Indiana; Los Angeles, California; Wells County, Indiana; ambulance service; An Architectural Atlas of Wells County, Indiana; barrel factories; cemetery tours; Christmas open house; Depression era teachers; fundraisers; fundraising; historical museums; historical society mission; historical society programming; History of Wells County, Indiana, 1776-1976; industry; local history; membership dues; museum displays; piano factories; racial prejudice; school tours; tax disbursement; volunteerism; Wells County, Indiana Family History, 1837-1992; Allen County Public Library; Indiana Historical Society; Ku Klux Klan (1915- ); McDonnell Douglas Corporation; Old Settlers Association; W.B. Brown Company; Wells County Historical Society; Colson, Hermine Wiecking; Deam, Charles C.; Fulhart, Anna; Goodin, Peggy; Park, David; Park, Fred; Scott, Everett; Weinhart, Sandra
- Buffenbarger, Wilbur, October 2, 1995; 95-024; Truesdell, Barbara; 25 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 60 minutes; index
  Wilbur Buffenbarger discusses the Noble County Historical Society in Albion, Indiana. He explains the historical society facility's history and how it was acquired. He discusses the quarterly newsletter,The Pioneer Echoes. Buffenbarger also talks about the historic landmarks in the area and the displays in the museum. Mary Leitch is also present during the interview. She validates most dates and names given by Buffenbarger.
  farmer; historical society president; Albion, Indiana; Noble County, Indiana; facility repairs; fundraising; grants; historic sites; historical society origins; museum displays; newsletters; volunteerism; Cole Foundation; Luckey Hospital; Noble County Historical Society; Luckey; Bender, Lloyd; Briston, Joe; Bushong, Harold; Bushong, Martha; LeCount, Joy; LeCount, Nelson; Rendell, Harold; Seymour, Harold J.; Zink, John
- Garton, Daisy Hinkle, September 26, 1995; 95-023; Truesdell, Barbara; 22 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 50 minutes; index
  Daisy Hinkle Garton describes the origins of the Old Library, Incorporated in Monroe County, Indiana. She discusses her membership in this organization and in the Monroe County Historical Society including the Genealogy Society. Garton describes acquiring the old library and the growth of the Historical Society.
  Bloomington, Indiana; Monroe County, Indiana; family history; fundraising; genealogy; historical museums; historical society facility; historical society mission; historical society publishing; junior historical society; volunteerism; Indiana University; Indiana University. School of Music; Monroe County Historical Society; The Old Library, Incorporated; Baker, Myra; Brandis, Elizabeth; Farmer, Mary Ellen; Harrel, Kay Beth; Miller, Rosemary
- Henry, Rachel, March 31, 1997; 95-030; Truesdell, Barbara; 21 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 55 minutes; index
  Rachel Henry shares her experiences with the Johnson County Historical Society. She discusses funding, the museum, new facilities, and publications. She also describes the Fall Festival and Christmas displays the museum coordinates. Henry discusses the establishment of the county and county history. Some of the topics she covers are the origins of Camp Atterbury during World War II and the settler experience.
  curator; museum director; Franklin, Indiana; Johnson County, Indiana; farming; fundraisers; genealogy; genealogy library; historical society board; historical society history; historical society publications; Indiana settlers; Johnson County Fall Festival; local history; log cabins; museum displays; museum history; new facility; newsletters; volunteerism; Alexander Hamilton Chapter, DAR; Camp Atterbury; Daughters of the American Revolution; Johnson County Historical Society; Johnson County Museum of History; Johnson County Public Library; Bergen, John V.; Branigan, Roger D.; Devore, Olive N.; Johnson, Grace; McNutt, Paul V.; Mitchell, Fred; Plummer, Mary Ann; Wetzel, Jacob
- Munier, Mary Ellen, June 14, 1996; 95-025; Truesdell, Barbara; 38 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 90 minutes, index
  Mary Ellen Munier, born in 1921, describes her work with the Jefferson County Historical Society. Her discussion includes the textile collection, museum displays, and remodeling. Munier explains broad goals and acquisition policies of the Historical Society.
  Jefferson County, Indiana; Madison, Indiana; archival cataloging; family history; garden tours; historic home restoration; historical society acquisition policy; historical society funding; historical society growth; historical society mission; historical society programming; Indiana roadside exhibit; local history; local industry; Madison Chautauqua Festival of Art; museum displays; museum remodeling; new facility; textile preservation; volunteerism; Cornerstone Society; Historic Madison, Incorporated; Indiana Historical Society; Jefferson County Historical Society; Jefferson Proving Ground; North Madison School; Pearl Button Company; Robus Leather Corporation; Windell; Dow, Margaret; Hines, Elbert; Imes, Mary Ann; Luddington, Link; Snyder, William; Woodburn, Peter; Wurtz, John
- Nordyke, Evelyn, September 7, 1995; 95-020; Truesdell, Barbara; 44 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 55 minutes; index; newspaper article copy about interviewee
  Evelyn Nordyke describes the growth of the La Porte County Historical Society. She explains the origins of the society and the community. Nordyke also shares her family background and her more than twenty year involvement with the historical society. She also discusses the society's newsletter The Old Letter.
  La Porte County, Indiana; donations; genealogy; historical society funding; historical society library; historical society origins; historical society programming; local history; museum collections; museum displays; membership dues; museum tours; newsletters; volunteerism; La Porte County Historical Society; Andrews; Bement; Ingersoll; McLane; Burns, Virgil; Coffeen, Ruth A.; Gunness, Belle; Langlois, Janet L.; Schultz, Fern E.
- Paarlberg, Horace; Paarlberg, Mildred, April 4, 1997; 95-028; Truesdell, Barbara; 29 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 50 minutes; index
  Horace and Mildred Paarlberg recount their involvement with the Tippecanoe County Historical Association. They also discuss the activities of the Association including the Feast of the Hunter's Moon, publishing, purchase of the Moses Fowler House, library, battleground museum, and genealogy workshops. Mr. Paarlberg also describes the financial hardships of the historical society.
  curator; Clinton County, Indiana; Crown Point, Indiana; Fort Ouiatenon, Indiana; agriculture history; archival cataloging; Feast of the Hunters' Moon; genealogy; historic site markers; historical association board; historical society funding; historical association library; historical society publishing; indexing vital records; Indiana State Fairgrounds; Indians and a Changing Frontier: The Art of George Winter; volunteerism; Wheatnotes; Agricultural Hall of Fame; Great Lakes Chemical Company; Heinz Pickle Company; LaFayette Journal and Courier; Monon Railroad; Moses Fowler House Museum; Prophetstown State Park; Purdue University; Tippecanoe Battlefield Grounds and Museum; Tippecanoe County Historical Association; Clark, Nicolas L.; Kwiatkowski, Phillip C.; Lilly, Eli; Martin, Fern; McCollough, Alameda; McMillan, Katie; Weirich, Nancy; Williamson, Maurice; Winter, George
- Sacopulos, Joy, July 7, 1997; 95-029; Truesdell, Barbara; 54 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 105 minutes; index
  Joy Sacopulos shares her experiences and involvement with the Vigo County Historical Society. She describes the society's beginnings and their financial struggles. Sacopulos also discusses the planning of many unique events and fundraisers. The society organized street fairs, historic theme events, cocktail parties, and an annual meeting to recognize their members.
  educator; Clay County, Indiana; Sullivan County, Indiana; Terre Haute, Indiana; Vigo County, Indiana; Wabash River, Indiana; Christmas display; family history; federal funding; fundraising; grants; historical museums; historical society origins; historical society programming; local history; membership; National Road; public library; publicity; toasting party; Vigo County Historical Society annual meeting; American Association for State and Local History; Association of Indiana Museums; Clay County Historical Society; Eugene V. Debs Museum; Indiana Historical Society; Indiana State Museum; Indiana State University; Indiana State University Tilson Music Hall; Indiana University; Italian-American Club; Rose-Hulman Institute of Technology; Saint Mary-of-the-Woods-College; Tribune Star; Vigo County Historical Society; Hulman; Jackson; Dewey, Susan; Dresser, Paul; Hulbert, Sam; Nation, Fred; Pickett, William B.; Vigo, Francis; Voorhees, Daniel W. (Daniel Wolsey), 1827-1897
- Schultz, Fern Eddy, September 7, 1995; 95-021; Truesdell, Barbara; 50 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 110 minutes; index
  Fern Eddy Schultz discusses her involvement with the La Porte County Historical Society. She explains the work she did in the archives, on the board, and on the quarterly newsletter. Schultz also discusses her hopes for the future of the Historical Society and its influence.
  board president; board vice president; county historian; La Porte County, Indiana; agriculture; archives; archives preservation; family relations; fundraising; History of La Porte County Indiana; historical society board meetings; historical society budgeting; historical society development; historical society mission; historical society newsletters; historical society publishing; indexing vital records; junior historical society; La Porte County descendents; local history; museum tours; newspaper articles; A Twentieth Century History and Biographical Record of La Porte County, Indiana; volunteerism; Allis-Chalmers Company; Indiana Historical Society; La Porte County Genealogical Society; La Porte County Historical Society; Northwest Indiana Genealogical Society; Pullman Company; Floering, Elizabeth Kenny; Gunness, Belle; Harrison, Hazel; Mennen, Fred; Tallant, Ruth
- Wahl, Henry E., September 14, 1995; 95-022; Truesdell, Barbara; 21 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 44 minutes; index
  Henry E. Wahl shares his thoughts on the goals, role, and history of the Monroe County Historical Society. He discusses the Wall of Fame Project displayed at Bloomington High School that is sponsored by the Monroe County Historical Society. He discusses his ancestry and the history of Monroe County, Indiana.
  board president; Bloomington, Indiana; Monroe County, Indiana; Bloomington High School Wall of Fame; community involvement; family history; fundraising; German ancestry; historical society programming; historical society role; letter writing; Letters From Honeyhill: A View of Homesteading, 1914-1931; local celebrities; local history; Bloomington High School (Bloomington, Ind.); Indiana University; Mathers Museum of World Cultures; Monroe County Historical Society; Pfizer, Incorporated; Showers Brothers Furniture Company; The Old Library, Incorporated; Bryan, William Lowe, 1860-1955; Butcher, Joseph; Carmichael, Hoagy, 1899-1981; Greevey, Henry; Kisters, Jerry; Lockridge, Ross, Jr.; Teter, Nellie Showers; Woodburn, James Albert, 1856-1943
- Wisener, Monisa, November 24, 1996; 95-027; Truesdell, Barbara; 33 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 90 minutes; index
  Monisa Wisener, born in 1932, describes her involvement with the Randolph County Historical Society and the Genealogy Society. She discusses the history of Randolph County. Wisener discusses the two publications of the historical society, and the growth of the society. The historical society has held many activities including fairs, restoration, a monopoly game and tours of their museum.
  county historian; health department registrar; Stanley dealer; Randolph County, Indiana; Richmond, Indiana; Winchester, Indiana; 1882 History of Randolph County; African-American population; cemeteries; genealogy; genealogy library; historical society funding; historical society museum; history fairs; History of Randolph County, 1990; industry; membership dues; monument restoration; newsletters; Quaker population; volunteerism; Randolph County Genealogy Society; Randolph County Health Department; Randolph County Historical Society; Randolph County Pioneer Society; Union Literary Institute; Tucker, Ebenezer; Wachter, Jim